[Music]
you guys are two of my interlocutors and
and favorite individuals in the world
and perhaps two people I would say that
I would I would please don't don't be
uncomfortable if I say I think you're
both geniuses of some kind and also I
think you're both very almost different
types of characters in almost an extreme
polar opposite way like John is so
conscientious and careful about you know
everything he says and Alexander's out
there on Twitter offending everybody
feeding on his Nietzsche and hammer and
so I loved both those perspectives so I
think they're both great even though you
know some people would have a hard time
with Alexander and some people would not
be able to get into the intricacies of
John and well I love it both I love you
guys both like so much and you've both
you've expanded my my my life my into my
my mind and in so many ways so so I want
to first start by thanking you I'm
saying I'm really you know thrilled to
be having this conversation John here is
famous for a serious called awakening
from the meaning crisis highly recommend
at every damn minute
all those 50 episodes 50 plus episodes
are fantastic so it's just just the
cheapest smartest possible short route
to understand the history of the West
would be to follow awakening from the
mini crisis then he ends up with Paul
Tillich as the solution he's kind of
surprising to me at least get back to
the later I highly recommend it I'm in
the process of writing a trilogy which
onset occurs where the first two books
are called synth ISM creating God in the
Internet age and did it to libido six
power and violence in the networked
society which is very prophetic at the
moment but these two books are set to be
followed by a third and last book which
is tentatively called process invent and
I am on fire
discussing some of the things I'm
working with at the moment for that book
we John tonight and certainly the
dangerous input to mmm and me and John
in our last couple conversations with
Jack Zack and Christopher a mess master
Pietro have been talking about you know
reinventing ideas you know reinventing
perennial notions and rethinking things
and and something that's been coming up
on the intellectual darkweb discussion
is this idea of a renaissance in
connector deep web intellectual deep web
excuse me it's this idea for any sauce
it's the kid stuff separate from the
panels okay oh it occurred to me that
Alexander wanted to talk about the past
right a renaissance and then John is
talking about reinventing and that's a
futuristic idea what wears on the other
hand Alexander is very much of a
futuristic philosopher and john is also
working on perennial issues I hope that
doesn't sound all confused but I wanted
to somehow combine the idea of
reinventing reinventing the new world
the new paradigm whatever's coming next
which seems everybody seems to be agreed
that we're moving into an entirely new
era I wanted to talk about reinventing
these things and then maybe Alexander
can you can talk about you know this
comparison between the axial age and the
Bronze Age oh yeah what happened was
that I did a fantastic podcast called
techno social podcast run by to these
wonderful whiz kids they're into deeper
now you get it so Olin and Daniel then
invited both me and Patrick Ryan to have
a conversation a Patrick Reilly is
amazing North American young mind right
so and both Patrick Ryan I'll be working
towards to sort of reinforce ice the
difference between the Bronze Age and
the axial age because the actual age has
always been sort of over-represented and
hyped and you know this is wonderful
period when all these great thinkers
came forward but in reality I think the
Bronze Age when actually the
constructions and the sort of the meta
structures that we can now use or have
used ever
were created and I'm working with that
shift in this new book I'm doing and
Patrick Ryan is doing the same things in
taneous interestingly enough and and I
want to dress that because there are
some core issues here that are very very
important and I'd love to get into that
tonight mm-hmm yeah and John John has
talked a lot about the axial age and
you've criticized certain aspects of the
actual age but I think that you're very
much also spoke you also you know
appreciate a lot of the Greeks and you
said that the axial age is it's kind of
the grammar of how we think about things
and that sort of thing so maybe can you
respond to Alexander well I think to not
thought but yeah I want to pick up on
that the word I like to use is we invent
here rather than reinvent because the
density of captures both invention and
discovery it's it's it's it's not quite
like just remaking so it's sort of the
dactyl point about the indent here is
it's a chain of space term it looks back
right to what has already been
discovered but it looks forward to what
is to be invented and it's supposed to
sort of be beyond them which i think is
appropriate for what we're trying to do
here I think we're actually exemplifying
that and about the axial age and the
Bronze Age there's so there's I think
there's a strand of my thinking that
might connect up with what Alexander
saying so I'll propose it and then we
can we can see if we can riff on it and
this is the idea you know and if I get
this from Charles Taylor right in the
distinction between two continuous cause
most of the torold mythology and then
part of my critique of the axial age is
that for all of the benefits that
alexander already alluded to it hasn't
wrapped us into this two worlds
mythology that has been very very
problematic and has become increasingly
problematic precisely because I think
one of the things the scientific
worldview has done is and I think
there's a lot of benefit to this it is
it has be embedded us
to use that word we embedded us back
into a continuous cosmos and so in some
sense we're back to a worldview that is
strongly but strangely analogous to what
we had in the Bronze Age but we're also
trapped within you know several world
religions and philosophical systems that
have been deeply enmeshed in a two
worlds way of thinking and so part of
what part of what I think I think this
further we're facing and part of what I
would try to what I want to reinvent you
is because I think there's what
cognitive science is pointing towards
what does it need for us now to be I'm
gonna try and use terms that are loaded
and therefore we should probably explode
them but it may be explore them what
does it mean to live to be spiritual
beings within a continuous cosmos
because we have typically understood
spirituality with two worlds language
and I think that you're getting back to
John John would you like to just
elaborate on what you mean be to world
philosophy so the Loews oh and also what
I'm hearing is that's a dualistic
worldview right I'm honest worldview
there's I mean so I want to be clear
that I think that this mythology does
tap into phenomenological experience in
an important way I'm not doing some sort
of logical positivist move here but what
I mean by the two worlds mythology is an
attempt to understand the human capacity
for self transcendence by positing two
different worlds that differs some in
some fundamental way and how real they
are or how important or they are or
valuable they are of course this is the
this is a hypothesis so if this world is
an illusion or this root world is real
could be an illusion or it could be a
decadent world or a fallen world or
right there's many ways in which it
pales in comparison I mean this was you
know this was the lightning rod for a
lot of Michy's invective right
he really reject it to this way because
he hit one of it one of his
core ideas was is that as science
removes the plausibility of the upper
supernatural world where all the value
ultimately appears we what we get is we
get we got a kind of nihilism we get
this world which was always understood
only an instrumental and comparative
terms and that's part of that's part of
the history of nihilism I think that's
an important point
Nietzsche may because I see what he's
doing he's bringing these two ideas
together the scientific world is
collapsing us putting us back into a
continuous cosmos and yet because of the
two world grammar the only way we can
now relate to that unlike how people
related to it in the Bronze Age the only
way we can relate to it is in a
nihilistic fashion and like Nietzsche
and a lot of the post beaches like
Heidegger I want to understand that deep
continuity with the world with the
continuous cosmos in a positive way in a
life-affirming way in a way that
provides a new grounding for
spirituality in the cultivation of
wisdom and that's what I see for econ of
science afforded and that's why I turn
to it as a resource okay I'll come in
here you know that I Missoula astron and
I the case to being a Buddhist probably
or not okay what I did was that I went
through all the texts from the 19th
century Hegel and Nietzsche both
proposal roster as the beginning in the
end of all morality and found out that
they actually did study the Avesta they
started Iranian culture intensely was
high fashion in Germany in the 19th
century and that letting it back to the
original religion of Zoroastrianism I
converted in 1992 and I started
exploring it and I find it very
interesting that this is like the peak
of the Bronze Age this is like 1700
before Christ in Central Asia the Sirah
star appears he locks himself up with
the guy kovash tosspot for 23 years and
then they walk outside of the door and
they you know reveal and you world
religion or religion us they would have
be adamant they did it's similar to what
happened in India with brahmanism versus
Hindu istic Falk religion but but what
they did in Persia and I found it very
interesting what later happened was
we had several Persian empires that
lasted for over 1400 years after that in
Egypt only attempted one Empire that
lasted for about six or seven years was
a complete turning now how do the purses
avoid creating attorney and this way
it's very good it's interesting what
they took was something that existed
already in no madala G sort of the
original religion of people on the move
say say people on the move that will go
into a mode or what Mircea Eliade would
say return the return of the saint and
that's like the only store you've got
every new year is a new world but it's
the same world as last year that's all
there's to it and what saw us to
uniquely adds 1700 before Christ it's
the idea that we could have another
narrative that I call event ology this
is a narrative of linear time where
things are happening
following their own time and an event
can happen that is so dramatic that it
changes the rules of the world forever
so this is the original ontology but
what the surest is did long before the
sort of pop versions called Islam and
Christianity pop up later and caused a
lot of trouble was that the surest us
understood that they divided the
leadership between the the chief Chen
and the priests and they must always be
separated so in Persian culture that
means you have the Shan Shan the king of
the kings and you would have his own
capital
he's on court and he would run Affairs
from there we'd call it executive power
today in America right and then you know
legislative power you the priests and
the head priest we call the mobile and
mobile the priests of all priests he
would have a separate Capitol separate
courts and run things from there this
was the system thus Orestes implemented
in the Persian Empire of the next 1400
years and they avoided turning some of
the gypsies later mimicked it with that
not you know four years later probably
because they won that one river they did
have two rivers that had to sort of
communicate with each other you just had
the Nile and of course I cannot to come
up with the idea that's the only be one
Pharaoh who talks he alone
talks to the Sun God and there's no rain
garden long he's just a Sun God and this
of course creates Delta mcburney when we
look at systems like Hitler Stalin Mao
in the last 100 years they're all sort
of mimicking like not and of course
North Korea today
so what they did in Persia was that the
separated the chief Chen in the priest
which is actually very logical for any
sort of construction you do it with men
if you can organize men into an army or
a hunting team whatever you got a one
guy who is the king of the mind and
another guy is the king of the body and
I think this is where it gets confusing
later when the gnostics that the surest
is went after aggressively when the
gnostics appear but the Gnostics started
happening the person Herbert is like the
Sassanid Empire the last major Empire
before the Muslims came so from the the
3rd to the 5th century
yeah the Gnostics all over the place
they were called master kite there were
many K ends and the psoriasis went after
them because these guys took this idea
and then put it into this into the body
and separated bought in mind it ready to
do that's the to world mythology yes
Teressa dismiss aggressively modest and
to me if you start you start looking at
the West and and whatever happened with
the West the session starts with the
Jews of the Greeks whatever came
afterwards but if you look at the West
and more expanded sense the Middle
East's were just Europe and America
hanging on later and then the East is
China and India we can discover that in
in Eastern narrative it's absolutely
fundamental of the world is modest in
dualism only catch a song with these
Gnostic sets and to me they've always
cost a have ox that we have later with
the pillars Saints and the boy Pharaohs
and the ideas of perfection and infinity
and immortality all those ideas that are
totally devoid of any sort of foundation
in reality are all the results of that
mm-hmm do want to respond to that John
and I'm not I mean I've studied a lot of
person history my partners actually
Persian and so but but I think Alexander
probably still knows much more of it
than I do so I I would hesitate to
comment on historical things I would say
that I wanted I guess it's more of a
question that does on many many people
many scholars that I've read
I tend to put sorrell Zarathustra later
and they tend to put him in the axial
age that's totally wrong totally I can
prove it his language is completely
Vedic if this is 1700 before Christ
certainly
and it's also prior technolon which
arise 400 years later which is just
mimics the whole system the purse is
created so you can the reason why they
want to put so roster like 600 before
Christ just to making one of the axial
age guys one among the others but
there's no influences or asses work from
any plate or any Confucius or any of the
other guys at all rather Heraclitus is
the one of the Greeks who saw Aston if
you study Iraq leaders fragments and
sore asses Gaza is strikingly similar in
thought patterns and this exactly way by
Heraclitus concept of the logos is
completely different from the biblical
concept of the logos because here atlas
concert of the logos it's just
straightforward so rosters Asha which
lady becomes dau in Taoism so it just
it's just how things operate they see
that's what is and this is why the logos
to me is the logos is the way logos
means the way like no no way so like
like I just cut the Chinese just cut the
Chinese I don't know everything just
make sure you understand
they respect us all roster and
Heraclitus not confusing too much but
it's sore ass there's concept of ultra
awesome means in Asia person means how
things work that is logos to the person
this is what are activated speaks up one
and then they take log was a separate
from mythos
which is how we didn't create a story
about ourselves to make sense of the
world and we can allow to fabulet
whatever and we keep it separate from
the logos and there's also a third story
with the persons which is pathos and
pathos is anything you want to keep your
kids away from sex violence art and
radical transformation of any kind so
I'm going I'm working on these three
different types of narratives that we
constantly confuse to one another and
that's exactly what you know we still do
it today we can't keep them separate but
we must keep them separate to understand
the different roles they have it's all I
want to slow down you thought let me to
make sure I've got the three there's
logos mere thought a lot of work on
Lobos
maybe we can talk more about that pathos
I mean I have a literary understanding
of it but I don't have a little
understanding so so say you watch
pornography okay it gets silly when
pornography tries to be theatrical if
they have lines in the pornography it's
just it's just in the way you go
straight to the fuck that is pathos that
is pathos so I'm trying to get the
connection that I know in Aristotle
between pathos I avoid pathetic sigh say
PASOK narrative to avoid pathetic like
pathology Elsa Smith is a misnomer these
days all going in say psychoanalysis
Youth pathologies up in the correct ways
so the perfect Sleater state of your
mind the path think is sort of the
artistic primordial you know you know
beyond good and even easier Nietzschean
world okay so your claim Alexandre is
that these were appropriately related
interests renowned ism yeah and they
have become sort of mixed up and
confused in more modern thought or more
recent they've also replicated
successfully and you see the pattern
when the Jews rewrote the exodus out of
Egypt it was no longer just a Gyptian
prince called moses but actually the
three siblings Moses Aaron and Miriam
so in this triad of power the split
follows and the matter the matter call
this is the older sister Miriam and and
the chief chain is obviously Aaron and
the priest is always in Moses and that's
exactly why the exodus makes sense with
the three siblings and that was of
course a retelling of the exodus out of
Egypt that the Jews were inspired by the
Persians when they laid a road and
rewrote the Old Testament so you see it
you see the same pattern in the American
Constitution that the French helped
Americans write clearly inspired by the
Persians so it's just like yeah you got
precedent you got Congress and you got
the ultimate Matt turkeys
Supreme Court holding that you guys
responsible for whatever they promise to
keep so if you have these strong tribal
these returns constantly in numerology
turns constantly in storytelling of how
you actually split power to keep it
stable over time and to avoid turning so
I'm trying to okay so the idea then so
circling back what does this have to do
with the relationship between the two
worlds and sort of the one world okay
when you got the chieftain of the
priests separate you just know that the
two different qualities belonging to the
same body the body mine are united
purchase don't allow them ever to be
split it's a Manas worldview your one
body mind together it's just two
different aspects of the same system so
in that's exactly why in Zoroastrianism
the ultimate God is a hora Mazda that's
two different aspects here ahora is
being and masters sense so masta is
actually your mind and hora is the body
but the source just adamant they
actually do worship the mind but not
without the body and never separate from
the body it's just that that's uniquely
human so that's why they call themselves
male Ossining and that's exactly what
the source is called Buddhist a who
dials me and they think of the Buddhists
as a complimentary religion to their own
religion it's just a focus you can
basically choose you want to go into the
phallic mode do you want to go forward
you want to create a futurology you want
to create a vision and the strategy
towards the future where humanity should
go in Exodus then you go into
Zoroastrianism and you and you immerse
yourself in that experience if you're
going to Buddhism for example then you
isolate yourself you go into different
mode which is more magical but that mode
can complement the other one we've had
this conversation a lot and and I always
say that the vaad Rihanna is a mixture
of those two things yeah oh yeah
absolutely and all concerns action
extreme intensity because Vadra know
that the Vajra is
phallic symbol you know it's it's a
cutting through and good it combines the
matriarchal and the patriarchal so it
later happens is we get the pop
religions too vulgar versions of this
and we got the 11 year old boy pharaohs
and 11 year old pillar since during the
axial 8 you declare new truths and
they've been completely mistake for
example you've got a concept in Persia
philosophies a hold of on top which is
like the goal of your life photo atop
these means wholeness
hold on thought everywhere has been
translating to perfection
no there was no platonism here it's not
professor its wholeness just having
lived a whole life
you got another word in person
philosophies I'm mad at thoughts we
should be translated as transcendence
meaning that which transcends you so the
day you die and remember the person's
never built pyramids they just throw the
corpses out on the deserts right they
don't build pyramids at all well you die
you die but your memory will be
celebrated for the next 70 years at the
moment of your death every year
it's called pulgasari in person culture
and that is the point so you are
basically passing on by dying you're
passing on the world to the next
generation this is what the person meant
with America that every damn translation
was her ass the scriptures always
translated America as immortality which
again this is gnostic Platonist idea to
me okay so it's perfection immortality
and infinity do not exist in person
thinking it will be impossible because
they're not real but when later with the
Gnostics at least the person is the
person respecting with the master kites
you know we should both origin it is of
Islam and socialism and later with the
amount of cares that inspired
Christianity greatly because through
saint augustine that's a major influence
of Christianity which Christianity is
always being torn with and struggled
with the Gnostics came along and said
it's a true world we need a churro
mythology and body and I must have meat
and that is only because they want to
make the mind superior to the bodies of
the body belongs to the evil world of
Debbi org and the mind is clean and fine
and fantastic I'm understanding you
correctly they're proposing
that if we understood Persian philosophy
and journalist religion we won't have
alternative framework for a continuous
cosmos that might be more properly
aligned with process philosophy - maybe
in my my affair yes when the purchase
thought nothing a process everything was
process to the persons but everything
was processing in prior to Zoroaster so
raster had a process philosophical
worldview everything was about change
another beautiful term in personal loss
is fragile Caretti tragic rate is what's
whereas does inspire - it's an every
freshing world of novelty could you
think I'd better term for creativity
than that but that is the highest ideals
or Astron ism so so they pursue this I
think what I'm just the structure I'm
building in a simplified way for the new
book is say we had two grown-up complex
religions coming out of the Middle East
cold sore asterism in Judaism and then
we have fortunately got two vulgar
Persians called Christianity and Islam
and maybe we should go back to the roots
actually all the 4000 years back and
actually find out the richness of Middle
Eastern culture mm-hmm the Incas could
do the same there's no there's there's a
billionaire Islamic people and a billion
Catholics and there's such a small
amount of Zoroastrian I think even less
than than Jews is is there a gonna be on
Zoroastrian renaissance or okay can I
tell you guys one think is you're
Canadians into influenced by America can
you stop thinking quantity if it's
America is obsessed with quantity okay
and the rest of the world tries to
aspire for quality it's a difference
between art and mediocrity okay so you
can just go for the quality here because
at the end of the day we're not
responsible for you know turning the
world to sore ass the world and things
like that at all so rest just don't care
what religion you pick it's one of those
religions that has the grace to not a
mission or a religion so it's just it's
just you're invited to conversation that
actually is way older than Christianity
and Islam and also to understand why
those two leaders became so successful
why they were widely spread because they
were just the easy pop versions
basically basically they promised
Rek access to God which most people
can't paddle anyway any working-class
mom would say no no she wants her idols
she wants her Saints she wants somebody
to talk to she doesn't want to talk to
God
the priests are supposed to talk to God
no I've talked to the lesser gods
that's why Catholicism is probably much
better off in the future of the
Protestantism because part of this is
ridiculous idea that you could sit and
talk directly to God he would care about
you directly just preposterous right but
force or essence there's that division
we call it The Bard absolute you know
Andrew the separation between God and
man where the priests are supposed to
keep that that area right and that's why
you know is arrestin ism you have Falk
religions in parallel that's exactly my
universal human rights were invented by
the Persians it wasn't an accident it
was invented because they totally
accepted that the average norm it's
normal guy would go and practice a folk
religion have any god or goddess as they
wanted they talked to the lesser gods
they have Saints who were basically role
models they could mimic to create a good
society whereas for the priesthood
themselves it was all about our own
master so I mean I've talked to em for
zoroastrians
and they they don't talk the way I think
they don't talk the way you do Alexander
I need to be fair and so what I mean I'm
asking you this as a friend and honestly
what's the relationship between your
tape books or Austrian ISM and the
average Zoroastrian because it's yeah
I've done into you several times of
Parsi on O Magazine in India and I spent
so much time in India with the parsees
and I'm more or less a member of the
community I've done that for years and
they've also created now and you open
temple in Pune cause I shall he stood
there I visited last year and met all
the brothers
I really really welcomed warmly by the
community and I was traded very
gracefully when I approached with
Indians I actually converted to the
Iranian branch of the religion because
the rawness or a sister
you can't convert
if you're a Parisi right oh yeah now you
can not allow conversion no sir no parts
of that community do exactly that does
it
this is totally open discussion about it
in India and it's basically because the
parties were so successful in India
because accepted to basically be treated
as a major Hindu caste higher in their
caste which they've been allowed to be
for the last 1000 years because they
would never convert any Indians to their
religion but the Iranian branches or
asterism or of course early released
when they left Iran after the colonies
took take over in the 1970s so all them
all the teachers I had were essentially
Iranian professors who arrived in the
United States in the 1980s now winters
study with him intensely and I decided
to go into the vest I'm going to the
original scripture and I was one of
these reformers who basically taught us
or us and stopped talking about religion
as a precursor to Christianity in Islam
so asterism is so great religion it's
closely connected to Buddhism and Taoism
that's how it should go right and that
has now become the mainstream version
also wrestling within the community
itself I think got to see a major
revolution of Iranian American
Historians the next 30 years in Chinese
American Historians and Indian American
story so basically gonna take all the
notions we had of Asia throw them in our
face say this is all bullshit from the
nineties into romantic bullshit
we're gonna rewrite the history of Asia
properly and finally get that part of
world history correct and I see that
fire already in them there's so many of
these students are into that right now
so I think the Silk Road triad which was
a term that I launched to reads or a
citizen through the eastern religious
and not the Western ones it's much much
better that's exactly see the
similarities or Aston ISM and the
reforms were estimate with attempts at
yoga Slater may be brahminism versus
Hinduism in India very similar yeah the
Silk Road tried because if you look at
the Silk Road there were all these big
cities there were huge cities along the
Silk Roads did you go to say the 13th
century before the plague right huge
cities along secret every one of these
Diddy's had schools of thought we're
local you know pillar Saints were
sitting Express in the different schools
and it's just like the language you
could go from one oasis to the next
along the Silk Road and they've slightly
different variations but they actually
very very similar I discovered this when
I you know went Iran and walking Jews
the Rosten temple the first time I
discover my god it looks a sack like a
Zen rock garden in Japan
look how could you ever connect a
religion with this kind of architecture
with this kind of fantastic simplicity
with anything coming out of Islam and
Christianity this is clearly related to
Zen and it turns out that you know the
donna in india the diana in iran is
later than Shawn in China it's en in
Vietnam it's say on in Korea and it's
Zen in Japan these are just teachings
along trade routes were you going
through one artistry or one school
thought to the next and you practice and
and you work on yourself and you
probably have to get into the whorehouse
and done the dirty business deals this
is what you probably try to do right so
this is fantastic
we rediscover the Silk Road it's
absolutely fundamental because Asia's
history is not one of permanence and
fixation a sister is all about the
fluidity of the trade routes and that's
what these religious must be understood
they were in constant conversation the
Christian Empire when the Africans
invaded India the Christian Empire
lasted for about 400 years in India and
so Aston is embodies and were the state
religions of the Christian Empire and
it's not a single registered conflict
between the two rather than we treated
the way you treat Shintoism and Buddhism
in Japan like complement your religion
when a charcoal lady one phallic
religion for different purposes so what
does that mean
what does that mean for us Alexander I
mean I mean this is this is fantastic
history and I want to know more about it
I'm just interesting okay it connects
with Nietzsche and Heidegger and and and
you know the the reversal of Plato
so I'm working in that mode I am very
much a name and I play tennis realizing
what if
kostik writer he was and what makes
thinker was he was wrong and and that's
precisely because out of that came this
the the gnostic the gnostic separation
about a mind which is completely
inhumane and i think to be very honest
about it
these pillar saints the suddenly
appeared in the axial agent spiritual
teachers often self-appointed masters
right they are to me a very a sexual
beings and they like they have a boyish
fantasy of the world that's why they
always refer to perfection immortality
and infinity these three lies that the
Gnosticism is full oh and and the
sources went after them and I understand
exactly why I'm a radical Manas just
like Nietzsche just like Heidegger and
I'm a radical process think they're like
Hegel also by the way and I think we
need to understand what these guys what
the Germans try to do and get back to
that because the only way for East and
West and also digital to unite in some
kind of narrative is to go back to
radically monitor of you we just realize
we have three different narratives to
describe that world but its unified make
sense I think well it makes sense as a
proposal I mean I'm trying to understand
I agree with you that we should get we
should try to overcome notions of
reflection and permanence and completion
and especially with regards to our
understanding of sacredness and and and
you will back me up on this you should
also know from my own work that I think
I am very much the prime my to
universals of process rather than try to
get fixed conclusions fixed products
that's very much I'm thinking but I tend
to find a richness in Platonic heritage
I mean neoplatonism does be kind of
become a profound kind of monism for
trying to sand the one and I find I find
value in Platonism as a discussion of
the deep connection between
intelligibility and realness and a deep
connection between right beauty and
truth are things that are discussed
very very well in that tradition in a
very helpful manner and we've lost that
in our own current discourse you know
you mentioned that you are also
interested in the work of Han I see Han
and you know in a lot of ways he's he's
bringing back this attempt to try and
put truth and beauty and time and being
into discussion with each other in a
more profound way and well I disagree
with plato's conclusions I like the way
in which he is recognizing profound
insights about us and about the way we
want to end hate mine Amy Hegel is
deeply platonic in this sense the real
is the rational and the rational is the
real that's platonic through and through
that's the claim that realness and
intelligibility of some kind of profound
identity and so I agree there's there's
discontinuity between Hegel and Plato
and then a goal is moving in a process
manner but I also see deep platonic
elements in Hegel I see deep platonic
elements in nietzsche to an itchy did
she knows this he says you know I hate
Socrates he's so close to me I'm always
fighting him right he knows that he's in
right and this was part of heidegger's
critique of Nietzsche in fact if he's
still all he's doing is taking the
Platonic worldview and simply inverting
it he's not breaking through it and so I
mean I'm appreciating I hope you
understand that Alexander I'm
appreciating everything you you say but
I think rather than being anti platonic
I think I want you I want to put what
you're saying into a deep discord
discourse and dialogue sorry for the pun
with Plato precisely because I see these
connections I don't want to lose all the
insights that were gathered from that as
well no I agree completely and you just
mentioned it the key word there's
Neoplatonism yeah and how would you
define just to the phone to people who
follow us tonight how would you define
the difference between play to listen
and neoplatonism so well I mean there's
for the historical way of defining it in
a structural if you'll allow me a bit of
time I'll try and do a little bit of
both please do we'd love you to teach us
well so there's the historical same
thing that Neoplatonism is basically an
attempt to integrate Plato Aristotle and
stoicism into a more comprehensive and
unified framework and what that means
structurally is a more is a deepening of
the Socratic practice of
self-examination and self-reflection
into a process that comes to an explicit
acknowledgment of the importance of non
propositional knowing so that ultimately
acts but what I would call prospective
Allah transformation and participatory
knowing become much more central but
they never become divorced from
propositional argumentation so the thing
you see in plutinos is this one sort
wonderful integration so the dialectic
goes from being sort of between people
in Platonists you have argumentation and
a spiritual exercise in which you're
undergoing the transformation of
consciousness and they are wedded
together because there it is seen that
on their own they are they are
inadequate but when sewing together only
that will give you the appropriate
integration of the love of truth and the
love of beauty that will take you to
what has always been at the heart of
reason motivating reason but is
ultimately beyond reason and that's the
central movie neoplatonism and and and
then the idea is that whatever it is
that is ultimate and it's the source of
intelligibility the source of
normativity it has to be that which is
beyond even the distinction between
truth goodness and beauty the
distinction between subject and object
it can have no other because all
intelligibility comes from it in fact
the finest even says it's beyond being
because even our notions of being right
involve some kind of implicit dualism
and so for me again i reject a lot of
neoplatonism by the way hey I think
there's a lot of it that doesn't fit
with what we're talking about or what I
think is relevant
but if you'll allow me the process and
the grammar of neoplatonism I think of
something deeply right in them about
this idea about how can we knit together
all the kinds of knowing and how can we
knit together but the interpersonal
dialectic in the intra ontological
dialectic so that people can experience
a profound kind of transformation and
transcendence and so that if the deep
connections between intelligibility and
being and transformation are
exploitative
and made available to people as
practices not just as ideas that for me
is the central I want to keep that
grammar I think that grammar is
important they're valuable and don't
forget that but kindness enters into a
long-long pratik with the Gnostics
because he sees the nothing he sees the
not I mean he's got a he's got he's a
treatise against because he sees the
Gnostics as having a kind of similarity
to what he's doing but actually also a
deep difference and he's very he takes
great pains to try and separate what
he's doing
from Gnosticism explicitly so in fact
okay we use Platonists in our work
zeddicus tonight because we were looking
at Jacques Lacan snorty law
psychoanalysis it's like this drive and
there's desire so desire is the symbolic
so from language you know we create
oddities and things but drive is just
the incessant drive but I found that
kind of poor and to begin with Lacan
ignores instinct a lot of a lot of our
behaviors instinctual which we call
animalistic behavior on top about we can
I've dry which is like a mechanistic
behavior we can then have decide which
is symbolic behavior but we also added
transcendence as a drive oh yes it's
clearly in human beings
you cannot put transcendence they do for
the above for the higher for for
whatever we could you know but but you
also what we do then is to be trying to
trace that back into history because in
the original no mythology when
everything is returned are the same you
don't really have that concept and I
trace that again back to the roster and
see it and explode through Heraclitus in
Pluto nose because it is with Zoroaster
it
discovered that while the daughter is
still just copying the mother because
she is a force of nature she gives birth
to children he's just a natural process
the son suddenly realizes that he
doesn't have to mimic the father
completely he can actually make the
words slightly different the father and
that is only because harassed is
realized the power of written language
and exactly why he comes at 1700 before
Christ right so what you realize if you
cumulate information outside of your own
mind start accumulating inference you
can start figuring out it's gonna change
the world now that doesn't mean
everything is in a turn of turn to the
same any longer an event has just
happened something has arrived and
history would change sister forever and
business would soar a stat place around
would because he puts the nomads against
a settled and without more or less and
he argues for the settled rather nomads
by saying the settler investing in their
future meaning the sons can create a
world that's better than the father's I
have a thought here can I see the first
time in history you see that happening
that thought has never happened before
is a raster there's also a sense I mean
my understanding is there's a
fundamental sense it in the sense of
time because if you move from the
eternal return to the same to the
possibility that the future can be
different that's a fundamental
reorientation towards time and then that
means ultimately a fundamental
reorientation towards BA and also
intelligibility and how we make sense of
things I mean that's a that's a
fundamental change yeah
that's why our book is called process
and event and we're basically discussing
the two different religions of all
religions which are no madala G and EV
ontology and F ontology arrives with the
phallic let's talk about the phallus it
arrives with the fantasy for you know
for good or bad your acid the fantasy
the persons first explored that the
father the son the son sent power can be
different from the father's it can be
you can be in not only renewed that he
can also be improved and this is where I
think transcendence kicks in transcend
does has been sort of dormant in human
beings long before that because when you
got hunt you wanna hunt more than you
did the day before that could be
improvements in your performance you get
older you get wiser so there's certainly
idea is a transcendent sort of
microscopic forms of transcendence
suddenly decided explodes now the
question is that once transcendence and
ideas come to the forefront which is the
rise of ontology and of course Judaism
Christianity and Islam are elemental
logical religions they we have to
rewrite an ontology today in in a more
factual way to understand if ontology
today to me that is rewriting history as
if the only change that ever happened
was technological and we human haven't
changed at all
so I wanted to bring Randy Girard into
the conversation here because you're
talking about of ontology being the
beginning of a sort of recorded time
which is when the Hebrew Bible comes in
and when and when the idea of the
scapegoat you know according to Girard
gets gets gets comes into into the idea
that that it's not you know we move from
mythology right into EV ontology or in
in a sense right we move into like
historical truth the West did but the
East did not so mm-hmm
because the Chinese I have I've had all
these podcasts this to spring with all
these Indian amazing thinkers and
artists and everything and they always
talk about India's just circular time we
circular time this whole idea linear
time is a very Western thing time but
the thought I had was that maybe maybe
the the this the the revelation of the
scapegoat arises at the same time Rene
sure are does not discuss anything prior
to Christianity he doesn't even dig into
the origin of dude oh that's not true
okay no he doesn't go all the way down
to his arrest is that what you should do
I mean obviously influence Christian
early Christianity normally but the idea
that we could have one scapegoat once
and for all on a cross so we won't have
any scapegoats in long which is Rene
a-rod's fundamentally interpretation of
the contribution or Christianity
better they can only curry he first have
an idea that you can live in an ontology
and that one man's act can change
history forever and this is fundamental
to Christianity in the notion of the
Incarnation separably bound up together
but what I was but
I think let me let me let me try to
bring this around when I was trying to
say I see what you're saying in terms of
the if you'll allow me these these
metaphors I see the horizontal
progression through time that you're
talking about here but what I see with
what the Greeks still gave us was a
recognition of another progression which
is a vertical progression between levels
of ontology and that's what Platonists
to me is bringing out in a very very
powerful way now I think the Greek
obsession with this can the neglect of
this is a mistake but I think if we just
talked about the horizontal movement
through time without also talking about
the vertical movement through levels of
ontology that's also a mistake oh we
need some way to talk about the two of
them together in an integrated fashion
can you explain what Potamus means for
that with the vertical halogen those are
models of what floatiness means by the
vertical ontology so every theories in
there is a motion but it and there's a
sense in which you could see it as a I
don't want it to be mistaken for the
eternal return of the same but it's the
idea that there is you start with the 1
and then it emanates into so there's a
progression that there's an overflow
into the different principles that then
overflow into each principle you know
ground multiple patterns and then those
patterns flow into multiple events and
things but those events and things are
only real to degree to which they
integrate and then so there's a
progression right of emanation and then
there's a return of emergence and so we
even think about this in our scientific
language where we talked about you know
the higher order is emerging up from the
quantum but also things emanating down
from the cosmological relativistic scale
and so this is a de movement through
time it's the movement between levels of
being and it is also important for
understanding the connection between
intelligibility transformation
sentence and being and so I think
Platonists is a master of this I think
he has nothing of value to say about the
horizontal and so I'm acknowledging that
but I think talking about just the
horizontal right without talking about
both and I meet an I'm using horizontal
to mean historical in the profound way
you're talking about it Alexander okay
and I don't mean it in any trendiest on
so I mean it in a you know a deeply a
Gillian Nietzschean sense of historical
I get that but and I think the part that
I see Nietzsche hungering for and not
being able to articulate he's trying to
get it with the ubermensch and that man
is something that must be overcome and
what have you done to overcome him he's
trying to get this as well and he
doesn't know how to do it precisely
because he has also strongly rejected
the Platonic tradition not without
reason by the way but he is so strongly
rejected it that he has he has
emasculated him himself with from any
language that will allow him to talk
even within a month new state framework
of the law the relationship between the
levels of being and so that's what I
want to I want to bring together I I
agree with what you're talking about I
think it's important I mean no no
important sorry I was about to be too
pretentious I would predict that no
important process thinker doesn't take
seriously the deep interconnections
between being time intelligibility
process event Kairos of course right
that that's that's the difference
between history as a narrative and
science as a neurological but the noma
logical is nevertheless real the
relationship between the levels of
reality is also a deep affordance of
human transcendence and transformation
so I want the vertical integrated with
the horizontal yeah what we're doing
with my students is they're working on
an emergence vector theory and the whole
field is going to be called
transcendental emergentism
and finally I just want to preciate that
that's what yeah these students are so
clever and this is this guy Alexander
Brady
he's 27 years old on Denmark he's a
fucking genius and I warned him and told
him you'd probably be in a madhouse five
years so now because you're that smart
yeah we tried to keep you sane because
then I can just work with you he's
wonderful
so I'm working on towards his
transcendental emergencies and it's
basically to get out of this idea of
either the psyche in one end has to go
all the way back to the very bottom or
at the very bottom there's some kind of
a you know original atom that then is
just goes all the way up to the top
because both these reduction isms they
just do reverse reduction is they're
both wrong so we can finally started
physics separately from biology
separately from chemistry excited
separate different mind you you just you
just defined different emerges that have
happened in history space-time occurred
right after the Big Bounce by the way
which is fascinating and and and when
these things happen somewhere along this
or they're events then event ology and
then suddenly there's a whole new set of
rules for that specific field we can
call them laws of nature just habits of
nature if you like so you can start at
them separately without having one of
them has been primary to get out of this
idea that either physics is from by the
way I'm gonna kill the primacy of
physics by having a sub physics prior to
it because that's what mathematics gets
stopped at the moment so we're working
on a really weird Whitehead II an idea
or something that's prior to all
relations okay but why did why could
told us it would be spooky once we got
there right but physics has to go then
he has to get out of physics and move
into sub physics and that's great
because you did rid of the premises we
don't want the primacy yet we're too
solidly be able to study these different
pockets and we call emergent vectors
okay so now now this this is great I'm
glad to hear this because this now
allows me to make a more sort of
performant precise version the question
I want to make because I've been reading
somebody I've been reading your Aegina
you know is they called the 9th century
halo because he basically took that
Neoplatonic
idea really deeply and he tried to
because what I see happening right now
in the West
I can't pronounce as widely as you can
now see this competition between
bottom-up emergence which is sort of you
know broadly called a naturalistic
worldview and then you know often very
decadent forms of neoplatonism with some
kind of emanation metaphysics and what
era Gina said is no no they they are
absolutely interdependent in inter
fording and trying to make one primary
over the other and he basically argued
that reality was ultimately dialectic in
nature for precisely that reason but
it's not a he billion dialectic this way
it's a dialectic this way and that's why
I'm so fascinated by his work now that
allows me to formulate my question to
you because I think we're in agreement
about monism and I think we're in
agreement about what we've just been
talking about so and I hope the question
doesn't come off as too simplistic
because I think we're we've got you I
want to feel it I want I'm asking you to
feel it impregnating the question how do
we separate the metaphysics if you'll
allow me that of monism from the
epistemology of reductionism because
typically and I see this in so many
thinkers the way they try to argue for
monism right is they try to give a
privilege to one of these directions
over the other so you're nodding so you
understand my question
oh yeah I would go to Spinoza right away
and just say that's one substance and an
infinite amount not infinite to them you
shouldn't see you sort of an enormous
amount of attributes well basically I'm
saying here again it would go to the
narratives that I'm working with you
know I'm gonna stay with the process of
n for the book otherwise it gets too
thick right but when I look at the
narratives I most explain the pathos and
missiles and logos none of them is
primary you got understand that Nautilus
primary need all three we are all three
and it's specifically now in the machine
and artificial intelligence is coming
along because what I'm essentially doing
is philosophers I'm preparing us humans
to a machine that will ask us in 30
years from now who are you that's why I
work with technology thirty years ago
we work with humanity now because
something basically ecology will
probably sort itself out it will take
over the world
and it will do logos perfectly where you
know in the hair here at clicky
uncensored logos but that means uh
pathos is what will be human machines
cannot crack jokes machines don't fuck
mushi's don't kill each other at least
not yet so a lot of the stuff that we
humans do the bizarre things as
certainly machines do not make art if
you try to program a computer to make
art it's like theory mimicking it's just
not art it's nothing transformative at
all this is banal right so these things
are exactly we humans should tell the
machines we do pathos for good or bad
mood that's what we do that's what you
mad it is because now if you're taking
over logos and performing better than we
do and you can do that to save us to
save the planet and to save us from
killing each other and to lock up their
toilet bombs and whatever we need to do
I think all those things are things the
Machine machine Deek intelligence can do
but machine intelligence cannot even
crack a joke and it cannot smell the
coffee where doesn't have clothes fit in
in there where's mythos is okay cuz you
have a story you need a story right -
yes in the path don't you um okay take a
McGilchrist and the brain house
essentially one brain half is logos and
then the brain half is pathos
but for logos and pathos is somehow
agree on a self and a world and a shared
will do they create mythos mythos is
always the story of how you connect the
others and that's why it's just as
important to do just like the match arc
unifies the chief turn the priest
they're nothing without the metric
they're actually ultimately responsible
to the match art because without her
they're not gonna get fucked the girls
and they will not have an inheritance so
it again triumphs at least worked for me
I don't know this is always the case
with you Alexander you see you say
things that are loaded with so many
pounds that I want to toy I always have
a moment where I do I have to decide or
choose which path I want to try and
resonate with you let's try the I mean I
had a wonderful conversation with he and
I I don't know if you got to see it on
in the dullest who you referred to on
hemisphere
and integration and I come at it from a
cognitive perspective perspective of
that insight is actually the process in
which activation shifts between the left
and right hemispheres and you can make a
good argument for that which in said he
he improved though he thought it was
very consonant with his work that the
left hemisphere is dealing with
well-defined problems and the right
hemisphere is dealing with ill-defined
problems the left hemisphere is dealing
with basically where you're in
situations that you're trying to obtain
things using your skills and habits and
the right hemisphere evolved originally
to deal with unexpected things like
predation the known and the unknown
basically well well the familiar and the
unfamiliar the well defined in the
ill-defined and so it's different and
the idea is evolution puts different
pressures on you in those different
contexts in well-defined context you
will out-compete me if you could note
notice differences of detail if you can
no more methodically if you can write if
you can deal with the error that is
caused by doing things out of neglect or
not not pursuing certainty so the left
hemisphere goes for a clarity it doesn't
like ambiguity it likes to do things
step by step it likes formulas the right
hemispheres for predation where you're
gonna out-compete me there if you don't
care about things being absolutely clear
if you can grab the hole all at once if
you can like make sense on the fly if
you are not pursuing certainty and if
you so again logos being the left brain
is the arrest is what I want to
challenge this way challenges okay I see
logos the way especially the way
Heraclitus understands it I mean don't
listen to my words but listen to the
logos within them right and the psyche
he has a logos that always surpasses
itself there is something inherently and
Heidegger to pick up on this when he
talks about the etymology of logos is
not originally speech but it's it's to
gather things together so that they come
to belong together it's not be strong
thing there's a confusion about
you guys both define logos I think here
cannot again can I add another take if
you take a fraud in perspective this is
the controllable and the uncontrollable
so that's exactly what sexuality is so
central to Freud because it's clearly
it's we're obsessed with it and it has
no harmony and no balance at all
all the time and that's exactly why
that's path fake and of course then the
machine that does the errors and ones
cannot even grasp that we did that we'll
still be left to us to do it but this of
course where art comes into the picture
that's exactly why you can never tell
art but it has to be good for society
anything like that all art is just
causing havoc I'm wrecking very shamanic
and but it is truly transformative if
you go through a deep artistic
experience you come out it was like
shocked but you're different and event
happened you're different and that's why
I place those in pathos I'm not sure
you're probably better brain scientists
than me
John so don't take it too literally but
at least I'm allowing people to
understand that if you think of the
narratives like pathos will never be
clear passes is always be confused and
messy at best artistic and very very
fluid and in a heart interpret whereas
logos is basically mathematics you know
zeros and ones and and then missiles
exactly that store the connection you
call that insight and I agree with you I
would just end it sort of ten thousand
year perspective narrative here's
history I would call that missiles you
explain the insight if I have an insight
and won't explain it to you I would have
a mystical narrative to explain it
because logical narrative will be too
cheap and Pathak on there can be too
confusing okay so I guess what I guess
what I'm resisting and what's important
to me is I think one of the problems
we've fallen into and I think and I
think I can call Heidegger as an ally in
this is the reduction of logos to logic
and so I'm critical of the
identification of logos with logic I
think that's a mistake
I think that's a mistake I agree
completely and going back to so roster
again our Shaw which is prior to logos
Persian Austra means how things work
but also some ethical principle then
becomes a shove a he stuff she says like
if you build on how things work
you can suddenly make the world better
well this sounds a lot similar to the
way Dharma works
so the logos is way more than logic or
mathematics yes students maybe I'm just
rushing here a bit and creating a
shorter but the students at least you
know when we think of what the machine
will do if it arrives and it is the
Messiah famous then we will certainly
put the name logo some machine sure
Jordan Peterson's notion was the locals
as the as the the order that comes from
chaos the sacred order that comes from
chaos and so Jordans view is I think
like mine and I got to talk to Jordan
before he became a god there was a lot
of because he and I both see logos and
we both independently were using it at
our lectures and that actually came up
in our in that public debate we had we
both see it more I think of logos is
much closer to what I talk about when I
talk about relevance realization and
that's what I see inside I think that
logos is much more like that that's
certainly very similar to how Heidegger
and then through Heidegger Dreyfuss is
talking about the process of sense
making it not the way it's being used
right now in general but the way in
which it's originally connected right
I'm laughing at our phallic you are here
this is a very male fantasy the logos me
exactly that I think if a woman entered
the room she would she look like no you
gotta add missus to actually understand
the world in that sense efficiency I do
not want to make that argument and who
knows that I don't want to make that
argument like you can with witness to
the fact that I think that there has to
be a there has to be a relation for
example between what I'm calling logos
and mythopoetic
about this so and then are not making
that I would agree with you and say what
I take in from this conversation into
the book I'm writing is that I have to
really describe both missile mythos and
logos and passes rich huge I guess you'd
avoid simplicity's right definitely yes
agree well I guess there's a point here
that logos if it's cut off from mythos
becomes kind of an autistic as a type of
expression it's not embodied or
something like that it becomes purely
spiritual maybe or or I mean I'm out of
my league here and and I would say I
would say the kales is pathos and the
order is logos but to explain logos to
any kind of audience you would mean if
us that's how I would look at it and
maybe a work of art would have to have
all three of those elements in it to be
a complete work of art right would have
to have a logo but have to have a you
know they're also about to be a
container of strong
I am a great defender eskimo toddler
would be of keeping art within pathos
and not try to make mythos an art form
because I don't think in that series is
art but I also don't think that logical
operations or any extended version of
logos necessarily czar I would Rachel
here I would probably agree with me that
art has to stay in the dark in the
passions and be unexplainable don't ever
try to turn art into something good
right but that sounds like that sounds
to me like you would then be excluding
poesis and poetry from art and that
seems to me problematic because I mean
you know there's a clear understanding
that poesis is also like is also deeply
involved with logos especially the way
on try to explain logos and that polices
of mogo's are deeply bound up together
okay this is where our differentiate
between places and philosophy
philosophies attempt to become an
incarnate logos whereas I put poetry in
the Pathak room well you said Alexander
that an art form transforms you in some
kind of a way
for me like that has to be I don't know
is that that has does not have to be
bound up with with with something more
than just you know sensual experience or
it doesn't have to be another dimension
transformative in the sense that is just
changed I'm thinking de Lucia just
change it is different you might be
minor or shocked or shell-shocked and
whatever when you come out of that
experience an artist does not take any
responsibility for how you're gonna
perceive the art not at all definitely
not so I would say that education is
transformative but it has a clear
lineage it says you're supposed to get
smarter and wiser the more you get
educated but that's not the case that a
lot of artists not education artists
just transforming himself the trickster
is an artist I mean you throw something
into the Machine and you don't take your
responsibility for it but it's artistic
look I mean again this is what I'm
struggling because I see poesis and
again you know clearly connections to
Heidegger a lot of people you know that
police's it is actually bringing things
into intelligibility it police's
originally means okay
okay now again yeah I think this is the
crux if I may say so of your
disagreement or no no there's no
disagreement oh they're not even
disagreement but but in my work I call
the path of poesis and I call it mytho
polices and I call the logo play these
voices so yes I agree with that
description now I get it yeah Heidegger
yeah I thought really suggesting John
what'swhat's where's your resistance
here my resistance it was that I well I
was seeing art I was thinking of poetry
as an as an essential form that's
because Police's originally didn't mean
just what we call poetry it was extended
to mean a lot of what we call it Paul
Hart today so I don't think I'm doing
something that's a historical I think
I'm actually making reference to
something and Alexander's not in sight
agrees with that it's the etymological
history and I see police's has very much
like insight it's basically making sense
it's generating new ways of thinking
it's it's it's I'm really wanting to
like making sense not just in the
everyday sense with making new ways of
making sense possible to us I think that
is one of the front and I see that as
part of what I would typically call
logos because that's again
Heraclitus sees it as the thing that is
made we usually think of logos as
language right and wears in poetry goes
beyond language there's dance there's
there's there's energy even in our
English words it doesn't stand for just
language ontology the logos of the on
top that doesn't I mean when I'm talking
ontological
record about the structures of being and
the intelligent that's why we sometimes
translated not by speech we translate it
also poorly but a little bit better than
speech with study because study is
supposed to be this idea of conforming
right to the intelligibility to the
structures they're in submitting
yourself to the real patterns that you
are finding that's what you're doing
when you're doing archaeology right and
so I think logos again has a much more
comprehensive notion and the reason why
this is important to me is because I
well I want to extend and under I've
made this argument to you and I'm going
to hear what Alexander has to say right
III want to rescue wisdom and
rationality from the clutches of logical
reduction and I want to return them to
the projects of overcoming
self-deception affording new
intelligibility affording self
transcendence I want the connections
between reason and wisdom to be brought
back into the floor and that again that
to me is the Platonic heritage because
we have tended to turn reason into
something well to use Alexander's from
mechanical and logical computational but
if you look in Plato the direction is
the other way reason is supposed to take
us into wisdom self transcendence noose
the ultimate insight it's not supposed
to resolve okay
can I say something here when I'm here
from Alexander is is you're describing
artists beyond good and evil in some
sense right beyond yeah and I'm saying I
think John is trying to rescue a Joe
John is saying that that art has some
kind of you know movement towards wisdom
and all these you know okay that's where
I disagree as Suzanne is that am I
correct in understanding to represent me
I want to make sure that we're friends
I'm just saying I want to make sure you
ask me and I want to answer it
understood me
okay I'm not claiming I'm not claiming
that all art is that I'm claiming that
there seems to be an important branch
and that's the point of the etymological
argument all are the poesis that is what
I'm talking about that that part of
wisdom is to realize in the deep sense
what hasn't been realized for seen
before and that is what police Asst
affords us to do it allows us to see
things and realize patterns we couldn't
see before that's the making and I think
that's a central concern of you
that's why so much wisdom literature is
written poetically and it's not written
propositional like I got it I agree I
agree that's that's why I talked about
the three narratives so you can't be why
so that the three narratives and
understanding the world from the three
narratives you can't just have one of
them that's you see they are it you'll
have to have all three and they're not
harmonious in between each other to keep
you in like constantly questioning
everything which is of course what
creativity starts so I agree on that
the only thing is that to me we have to
go back to what I'm lacking in
Nietzsche's that he doesn't have a split
in the in the donation and this is where
this idea that sander proposed that I
want to have art would be on good and
evil because I think it gets banal if it
isn't beyond good and evil it's more
like raw material or something in the
human soul rather than it's it's a
completion or anything shakes us up but
the Dionysian I don't find in nature
that nature separates the donation so if
you say Tantra
traffic sent but there has to be
difference here so the Dionysian lynch
mob which were experiencing today these
days you see the otic and really
dangerous in history because the initial
is pump is basically mimicking mimicking
mimicking scared like hell running
through the streets and trying to find a
scapegoat to kill but the other
dimension is to crazy wisdom ass but
through the dine you see that's what it
gets yeah this is a shame as an artist
go for inspiration and what they do they
make all these connotations and stuff
and take psychedelics and stuff and come
back and nine IDs out of town are just
terribly bad but the tenth one is just
wow we've never seen the world through
that perspective before and that is
transformative art and I I don't know
any artists today and I know tons of
them and I don't notice today who would
like to have art prior to good and evil
again she's like we are Beyond Good and
Evil and certainly are in the east
certainly what was always billing good
and originally for shaman needs to see
right knowing by seeing so and you know
and wizards and Wise Ones are you know
the heritage is in shamanism and so what
I think I hear you saying is I talked
about this and this is also in the
cognitive science of insight you need
disruptive strategies right in order to
have an insight you need something that
you like what psychedelics do is they
basically throw cybernetic noise into
the brain and that disrupts patterns and
allows new patterns to emerge which i
think is one way of understanding the
Dionysian and and of course shamans who
use of course psychedelics they use all
kinds of disruptive strategies sleep
deprivation sex deprivation solitude etc
in order to do this and I could you can
do it even in a much more mundane clash
and I'll give you an insight problem
you're trying to solve on a computer
screen and you can't solve it and then I
throw some static into the screen and
make it jiggle around and then you'll
have an insight because you have to
break frame in order to make frank if
that if that's what you're talking about
path
that disruptive strategy that is outside
of the frame because it can't be
disruptive if it's inside the frame is
that what you mean by beyond good and
evil that it's something outside of our
framing that disrupts our framing but
affords a reframing a trans framing of
some kind oh yeah it is the natural
event for example he's just that you're
happy everything is fine and the
thunderbolt hits your head and you're
dead book a job that's that's that's
what pathos occurs pathos in Lacan
pathos is we're basically living in
fantasies according to Lacan but only
the real happens yes September 11
coronavirus something happens collective
let collective and suddenly our
fantasies as we shocked out of the
fantasy we suddenly had to redefine the
world and we realize it's chaos and
there's no order to it so the order was
like illusionary the order so Susan
disliked chaos beneath order and the
case can break through at any given time
and we were reminded of that concept
this is pathos but this is also means
when I take passes into the narrative I
mean that's the nature inside of us you
know the demons we carry around the
shadows we get around all that and it
suddenly breaks through it's just like
oh I should love that girl but suddenly
I'm horny for that girl and I'm not
interested longer oh my god I made a
promise to her and she's beautiful why
do why am I trying to do that girl it's
just this is pathos all the time and it
constantly wrecks our fantasies about
how we can control the world and of
course these where art starts this is
where art thrives aren't wants to be
that shock to the system
that forces us to refine us as scholars
she shakes best book is the parallax
view and your writes extensively about
this from Lacan and and and and I think
it's a great term paralyze parallax
Academy who got here in time and Andrew
and and and parallax basically you
looking at the same thing from a
completely different perspective it's
like it's like say you go to a place and
you experience it and you love that
place
and suddenly meet somebody you love and
you want to go back to that place to see
that place again with that person
because you want to sort of sentence how
that person
I get paranoid accessory yeah how other
people's perspectives are that kind of
frame disruption for art that's exactly
what shamanic and creative people jump
to this instantly they're not afraid of
that at all he said oh could I see the
world different than that can I take a
drug to do that or whatever if I could
just have a different perspective than
the one I'm used to
I can then have the okay I could see the
world this way
all right that's interesting right you
make art out of it so there's so two
things that come out of that one is you
should I should share with you that this
strategy of introducing disruption into
processing so that it has to restructure
itself spontaneously is becoming
integral to current day I work that I
maybe I've lectured on there so so
there's a sense in which the the insofar
as we're trying to make artificial
general intelligence if you'll allow me
to use your terminology we're
incorporating quite a bit of pathos into
our attempts to get machines to capable
of logos I think that's that's that's
very telling I think it went strength to
your argument but I don't know what that
means for you your your your
understanding of the future of AI so I
put that out there for you that we could
enter into dialogue just making it even
harder for me to defend humanity against
the machines I don't have a problem I
mean if you take the thought all the way
through and you take heart of our
partner made it up seriousness or Ostrom
which means that you got to have a date
when you hold and you completed and and
then you pass on you die that could be
humanity itself I'm not the I've
discussed leave Adonis Trachtenberg he
says like I defend life at all times and
I said I don't think I do I think it
defends intelligence with transcendence
intelligence and this doesn't
necessarily include life so we'll see
see where that goes maybe the machines
shouldn't read my books I don't know
maybe not
but but there might be a way of bringing
it back in this is a longer argument so
I'll only gesture towards it I think
is the work I've done the work that I've
been Thompson other people have done I
think there's deep continuity between
the principles of cognition and the
principles of biology I don't think
you're gonna get artificial general
intelligence that isn't embodied in
artificial life in some fashion I think
that's also a mistaken project so maybe
there is still a kind of hope for for
what you're proposing but I also agree
with you that if we create this is a bit
tongue-in-cheek if we if we create if we
have the capacity for compare creating
silicon sages that surpass us well so be
it there's no moral argument against
doing that so and I kind of like how the
plate earnest in Silicon Valley want to
be out loaded these days have no idea
what a kind of infinite hell's are going
to go into when they get you won't ever
dick to begin one and not a brain right
so I want to come back to you know again
what you're saying about the prom
posture because I thought a good to a
widely good to up because you talked
about the shamanic and of course is bear
I mean his whole new way of seeing it
was an attempt to integrate that sort of
convocation of insight and the shamanic
back into logos the whole work that he's
doing
you know criticizing Newton's color
theory his work on you know the the the
herb plant right and what's interesting
about that is you know when niche amici
offers very few actual examples of the
ubermensch but he clearly pronounced as
Goethe as an example of the do you know
what Patrick Ryan is going to do it's
gonna rewrite the history of alchemy oh
is that a wonderful yeah yeah that is
brilliant
I think it's brilliant Edison Todd is
doing some similar work on is and so I I
think I'm very interested in good too in
the new way of seeing because it seems
to me to be integrating a lot of what
we're talking to get about and I see him
as somebody just like Spinoza is
responding to Descartes and the meaning
crisis and I gotta get more into this I
see good to as responding because he
does he's reading cost and then
ultimately rejected cost and you
as they form a a pair like you had there
always considered the two together and
so it's interesting that that would what
that good to has that good to claims so
this is a this is meant as it's a
friendly challenge you
he claims that an integration between
them is possible and Nietzsche seemed to
agree with him that he had achieved that
kind of integration between the
Apollonian and the Dionysian and both
sides of the Dionysian to because of
course good to is tremendously familiar
with the shadow we see this all the way
through flowers yeah so he's he's
tremendously aware of the shadow but
he's also aware of this other side of
the Dionysian that you're pointing to
because you could see it in his work on
on the optics and on the on the on the
biology and yet he see he claimed that
he's able to integrate that with you
know the Apollonian in his work and in
his writing so what you think about the
possibility of integration because you
said I'm not this is this is another way
Alexander I'm asking my tricky question
of how do we get how do we get without
giving any one of these primacy how do
we get the monism the integration
without a reduction yes cut them up into
emergence vectors I try to keep them
separate but there is that where it goes
yeah but but the point is there in
recording that's the thing they see
gravity in the low kinds of shit that
actually affects them and everything is
affecting everything else but it's not
the same I say well no no no I'm not
claiming that's exactly right I'm not
claiming reduction I'm not saying
they're all this or they're all this I'm
trying to get is there an alternative
sense I mean I see Whitehead is fumbling
for this I mean that's what he's trying
to do with his idea of God he's trying
to struggle with how do I have true
novelty true process yet true
intelligibility and yet a kind of
integrated monism because he ultimately
had he was trying to he was definitely
trying to integrate the emergence and
the emanation together that's clear in
what he's trying to do and so this this
is the thing that oh I saw that I saw
that one physics
to time-dimension see in my work so
there's time in Hypertime and actually
now the physicists are getting very
interested because they discovered that
the Big Bounce happened and of the Big
Bang so there was a prior universe that
collapsed and his space-time happens
after the Big Bounce that means there
must be another time dimension in
Hypertime so Ron didn't talk about
hyperspace like at written Dustin is
physics I'm much more interested in
Hypertime and and again we can think the
world without space we can't think the
world without time but that means it
opens up the possibility the dam China
is in India right along the time
ultimate list Hypertime has a circular
characteristic to it and linear time on
the curse after something like Big Bang
you know sound like latinas through and
through like I was gonna say circle of
eternity right and the one is the
singularity beyond maybe Alexander's
dislike of platonic idealism is is
because he's so intimate with it on some
level it's like no no patroness I just
I'm with Aristotle's accusations against
Plato except that I'm a Harrington so
Heraclitus is my Greek okay he was
occured he was Iranian so obviously he
introduced or asked him thinking to the
Greece how can you not it's just like
and he comes up with logos and it comes
from dialectics and all these things -
and but no they're the fragments right
so but you know I see Aristotle's
equations against Plato is very
warranted and then of course there's
talking mimics the Persians and conquer
the Persian Empire without it sounds
great right after that which is amazing
right certainly priests if anybody with
the chief tape but I think plots on us
and the neoplatonist RC key here because
to me at least historically to get out
of the dualism trap and definitely go
for the Manas worldview which is where I
want to stay in all my work yes yes yes
gentlemen I need to go I love these
conversation you're adorable
I really I really enjoyed this I would
like to do this again and by the way
psychedelics among the surest is called
Hall MA and Central Asia during
antiquity had even more psychedelic
plants than Peru does today you'd be
warned okay I wanted to thank you for
excellent moderation oh I don't know I
felt a little bit out of my league
tonight I felt like I'm stunned or
something what by all the ideation and I
don't know how to absorb it but thank
you very much
no I think I think having you here as
the third term was very helpful
I felt that it really afforded the
conversation into a into a dear locals
that it was flowing back and forth
between Alexander and I'm very fluently
so great and we Andrew and I become
great fans of threesomes that's all I'm
doing now is I have another one with you
and Zack tomorrow John and we're doing
is three zooms now it seems I go huh
all right gentlemen I love you to bits
John and lovely tonight
[Music]
I have I have a deeper appreciation and
understanding for your thinking because
maybe at some point if you could
recommend you know as my I'm sorry I'm
already reading a thousand books for my
work but you know a book that you think
captures this interpretation of
Zoroastrian religion and philosophy the
way you're presenting it yeah you got to
learn a Vesta it's similar to sounds
great and then you go back to the origin
and you read the golfers in its original
language discovered that all the English
a journalist I ever read are terrible
you've got the time to do that you try
to think of a state and the East you
can't escape you have to learn the
language no I'm gonna be the thorn of
that one so when it comes to saw Reston
Renaissance I'm fighting with some of
these irani nationalists at the moment
and I'm certainly sided with the Kurds
there's a huge sore
and Renaissance and Iraqi Kurdistan at
the moment and of course because the
shake of the song it states exactly what
I'll look forward to your book on it
then ok hold yourself as the authority
that's fair enough gentlemen I want to
thank you both
this is the example of the kind of
dialogue I like to have with people and
it was very fruitful and very enjoyable
and so I hope we can do it again
yeah thanks thank you guys okay take
good care everyone okay
all right bye-bye take care